Guide to the Ann Henshaw Gardiner Papers, 1723-1981 RL.00432
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ann Henshaw Gardiner papers
1723-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gardiner, Ann Henshaw
RL.00432
15 Linear Feet
Ann Henshaw Gardiner was a nurse, scientist, historian, and one of the founders of the School of Nursing at Duke University. The Henshaw and Snodgrass families were farmers and politicians in Virginia and West Virginia throughout the 18th, 19th, and 20th centuries. The Ann Henshaw Gardiner papers include legal and financial documents for the family, including materials related to enslaved people, as well as photographs, scrapbooks, local history and genealogical materials, and materials documenting Ann Henshaw Gardiner's career as a nurse in World War 1 and at Duke University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Diaries, Financial Papers, Legal Papers, Genealogical Materials, Local History Materials, Photographic Materials, Scrapbooks, Miscellaneous, and Oversize Materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Some materials in this collection are fragile audiovisual/photographic formats in the form of nitrate negatives that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Ann Henshaw Gardiner Papers were acquired by Duke University through purchases and gifts 1965-1984.
Collection Overview
The Ann Henshaw Gardiner Papers begin in the early years of the settlement of Berkeley County, Virginia, with two pioneer families, those of Captain William Henshaw of Springfield MIlls, Mill Creek, and of William Snodgrass of Clifton Mills, Back Creek. Both groups married into other prominent families of the region, so that their papers furnish two hundred years of local history and genealogical material for Berkeley County. The Andersons, the Verdiers, the Turners, the Evanses, the McConnells, the Pendletons, the Robinsons, and the Rawlingses, among others, appear throughout the collection.
The early letters are predominantly business in character, concerning the land transactions of John Turner, the surveyor of Berkeley County who registered the land titles of many local families. He was related to the Snodgrass family through his marriage to Ruth Rawlings.
By 1814, the correspondence is centered in Robert Snodgrass and his brother Stephen. As Berkeley County produced wheat in abundance, the sale of flour from its mills became increasingly important. The Henshaws of Mill Creek in particular left records of sales of large quantities of flour on the Alexandria and Baltimore markets. The Snodgrasses in this period were also milling although their records are not as numerous for their sales.
Both the Henshaws and the Snodgrasses were involved in the political affairs of Berkeley County. Levi Henshaw (1769-1843) was a gentleman justice of the peace, captain of militia, a member of the county court and of the Virginia House of Delegates, and sheriff in 1840. Robert Verdier Snodgrass (1792-1861) was commissioner of county revenue, a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, and colonel of the 67th Regiment of Virginia Militia. Their papers reflect these offices, both in the correspondence and in the legal papers. Levi Henshaw (1815-1896) married Sarah Ann, the daughter of Robert Verdier Snodgrass, thus uniting the papers of both families.
Berkeley County was an agricultural community, whose conditions were reflected in references to slaves in estates, as runaways, and for sale or hire.
Robert Verdier Snodgrass was concerned in both Democratic politics and legal business with Charles James Faulkner. His son-in-law, Israel Robinson, wrote to Snodgrass of political conditions in Washington, D. C. where he was an office holder. (Later Israel Robinson became clerk of the county court, a judge, and a Confederate general) The son of Robert Verdier Snodgrass, Stephen, became postmaster at Hedgesville, Va., in 1855.
By 1860 the settlement of various family estates reveals a maze of Snodgrass relatives. A letter from a cousin in 1860 comments on John Brown's raid and the arrival of the Japanese Embassy in Washington.
The outbreak of the Civil War shows divided political opinion in the family. In 1862, a letter describes the condition of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad in wartime and of the Negroes in Washington, D.C., where slavery had been abolished. Stephen Snodgrass, a Unionist, did not have an easy time at Hedgesville during the war, and he had to have papers attesting his loyalty. On May 12, 1865, comment is made upon the assassination of President Lincoln.
Henshaw papers predominate after 1865. Business is dull; the collection of money, difficult.
As the family has scattered, letters of cousins come from many places, and grandchildren write to Sarah Ann (Snodgrass), the widow of Robert Verdier Snodgrass.
The first William Henshaw (1736-1799) in Berkeley County had married Agnes Anderson. William was the son of Nicholas Henshaw who came from Philadelphia to Berkeley County; thus Nicholas is the settler, William the first of that home. In 1886 correspondence begins about the history of the Anderson family; letters continue into the twentieth century.
By the 1890's Valley of Virginia Henshaw and her sisters, Mabel and Francis Little Henshaw, begin to write letters about genealogical matters; in particular, the Rawlings family is the subject of great interest.
Mabel Henshaw married Dr. Samuel H. Gardiner. Her concern for history led her to teach at Shepherd College, Shepherdstown, Jefferson County, W. Va., where she also served as librarian. Mrs. Gardiner was a district chairman of the West Virginia Equal Suffrage Association with correspondence in 1915 and 1916 which reveals the methods women were using to insure the pas sage of the woman suffrage amendment to the Constitution of the United States.
The daughter of Dr. and Mrs. Gardiner, Miss Ann Henshaw Gardiner, historian, scientist, and teacher, founded nursing education at the Duke University Hospital in 1930.
Between 1926 and 1930, Mrs. Mabel Gardiner wrote to many friends who remembered details of family weddings in the mid-nineteenth century. As late as 1940 she corresponded with R. B. Woodworth on the history of the Tuscarora Church and other Berkeley County churches. A picture of the Tuscarora Church is with these papers. (See Picture Cab. II-7)
The heart of the Ann Henshaw Gardiner Papers is the collection of legal papers which date from 1763. Both the Snodgrasses and the Henshaws as justices of the peace and county office holders were involved in a great deal of legal business through the ions. A grouping of legal papers for both families is followed by special sections on land surveys, on estate settlements, and on militia.
The general file of legal papers begins with gants from Lord Fairfax in the 1760s, when Berkeley County was still a part of Frederick County, Virginia. Richard Rigg, the land agent for Lord Fairifax, was the first surveyor in the district settled by the Henshaws and the Snodgrasses. Rawlings family deeds appear in the 1770s.
At the end of the Revolutionary War, John Turner appears as a chain carrier for the land surveys of the County. He became county surveyor, an office which he held until his death in 1811.
Among the family wills is that of Nicholas Henshaw (died 1777). With the deaths of Robert and Stephen Snodgrass in 1830 and 1832, a great deal of administrative work for their estates enters the papers, as Robert Verdier Snodgrass was appointed executor for both men. (Robert V. Snodgrass was the sone of Stephen Snodgrass) David Hunter and Israel Robinson are the clerks of the county court in these early documents.
Schools, roads, runaway slaves, the hiring of servants mail are concerns Which occupy the papers. With the death of Robert Verdier Snodgrass in 1861, his estate is settled and the legal papers belong to the Henshaws from that date.
The second division of legal papers concerns the settlement of a number of estates, usually those of relatives. The Turner and Gorrell families had intermarried with the Snodgrasses and Henshaws. The earliest papers dating from 1798 contain the will and estate inventory of Joseph Evans. Israel Robinson was executor of the estate of Elan Miller in 1849.
A large group of legal papers concerns the acquisition of land, basic in Virginia economic life in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Survey plats began in 1753 in old Frederick County, which had been established in 1738. From it Berkeley County was created in 1772. The first surveys, made for the Rawlings and Morgan families, were for land purchased from Lord Fairfax. Richard Rigg, his surveyor, signed the plats showing the Fairfax grants. Rigg is followed by surveyors Thomas Jones and Josiah Swearingen. Many names of early settlers appear in the survey papers. In the 1780' s a chain carrier, John Turner, began to make surveys. He married Ruth Rawlings, whose land plats are in the papers. John Turner became surveyor for Berkeley County and remained in office till his death in 1810. His son Thomas, who was his deputy, succeeded him as surveyor for the county; The estate papers of the Turner family, elsewhere in the legal papers, show them as early residents of old Frederick County.
In 1803 land office records appear in conjunction with the survey appears. By this time Robert Verdier Snodgrass was a county commissioner of revenue who worked with the Turners in the sale of land.
The Snodgrass family was involved in militia affairs from 1798, when Robert (d. 1830) was a 1st lieutenant in the 67th Regiment 16th Brigade, 3rd Division, Virginia Militia. This county regiment was divided into local companies, each of which was subdivided into classes of roughly seven men. Class rolls, rosters, and officers' lists make up the official papers. By 1820, Robert Verdier Snodgrass was serving as an officer. He became colonel of the 67th Regiment in 1838, thereafter making annual returns.
The constitution of the Berkeley Rangers was drawn up on November 26, 1859, to organize a company of militia from Berkeley County. This company is listed as the Berkeley Border Guards Co. D. 2nd Virginia Infantry, C.S.A. Army, under J.Q.A. Nandenbousch of Martinsburg.
The financial papers are divided between Levi Henshaw I and II and Robert Verdier Snodgrass. Bills and receipts, loans, and household accounts increased as the nineteenth century brought a less self-sufficient life on the farms of Berkeley County. The Snodgrasses no longer lived at the Bill on Back Creek, but had moved to Hedgesville.
With such long family histories in Berkeley County, it was to be expected that descendants of the Henshaws and Snodgrasses should turn to writing the history of their section of Virginia. Valley of Virginia Henshaw was a leader of the Daughters of the American Revolution in Berkeley and throughout West Virginia. Her sisters, Mabel and Frances, were in Martinsburg by 1916. They were the children of Levi Henshaw II and Sarah Ann, the daughter of Robert Verdier Snodgrass.
Mabel (Henshaw) Gardiner wrote a thesis on the history of Martinsburg in 1930 for the degree of Master of Arts at the University of West Virginia. This work was developed into Chronicles of Old Berkeley by Mrs. Gardiner in collaboration with her daughter, Ann Henshaw Gardiner. Published in 1938, this history is based on the Ann H. Gardiner Papers and contains the diaries which Captain Levi and Hiram Henshaw kept on trips to Kentucky, ca. 1828-1830.
Ann Henshaw Gardiner graduated from Shepherd College and went into training in nursing at the Massachusetts General Hospital. She saw service in World War I in a United States Army base hospital in France (U.S. Base Hospital NO. 6). In 1927 she wrote her thesis The Development of the External Form of the Squid Embryo, at Kansas State Agricultural College for the degree of Master of Science. With the manuscripts of this work are pamphlets and papers of Francis Noyes Balch on Cephalopods.
Broadsides and pamphlets refer to Berkeley County and its history, to estate sales in the county, to the Whig Party, to the militia, and to the Free masons.
Clippings pertain to family members and to the story of Martinsburg and West Virginia. A series of articles by B. F. Voegle on local history is also in clipping form.
Among the miscellaneous material is a manuscript arithmetic book, 1790-1791, which was used by Robert Snodgrass II.
The volumes contain a number of old account books and other records. Family data for the Snodgrasses is preserved in their Age Book, 1821-1861 for each generation from William to Robert Verdier Snodgrass, as well as a list of the family slaves and their ages. Daybooks and farm books date fray 1803 to the 1840's. Four postal card albums, an autograph album, and scrapbooks with many other miscellaneous volumes are in the collection.
At the end of the papers are two albums and two manuscript histories of the first ten years of the Duke University School of Nursing. Pictures, programs, invitations, and clippings in the first album document the beginning of the nursing program in 1930. In the second album are photographs of nursing and laboratory classes
A number of letters, poems, and pamphlets unmounted in albums, conclude the nursing papers On December 27, 1934, the Duke University School of Nursing Alumnae Association was organized with a constitution. A reprint from the Southern Medical Association Journal contains the speeches made in April, 1931, at the dedication of the Medical School. Among the pictures are a number of photographs of members of the various classes of the Nursing School. The Henshaw family is well illustrated by pictures of individuals, their homes, and antique furnishlngs. For further details on this collection, see F. Vernon Aler, History of Martinsburg and Berkeley County, West Vlrginia; Willis F. Evans, History of Berkeley County West Virginia; and A. H. and M. H. Gardiner, Chronicles of Old Berkeley.
119 items and 9 vols., added 5-30-71, are letters, financial and legal papers, and scrapbooks and albums of the Henshaw, Snodgrass, and Gardiner families. Manuscripts of the early nineteenth century pertain to the settlement of estates, land transactions, and the hiring of Negro slaves and their deposition. The volumes center in nine scrapbooks and albums - five of which contain post cards of France and all of which are illustrative of the career of Miss Gardiner.
1 item and 1 cassette tape added, 1-24-73: Copies of the address Miss Gardiner gave at the fortieth anniversary banquet of the Alumni Association of the Nursing School of the Duke Medical Center, April 10, 1970.
2 items added, 5-5-84: Letters written by Robert Verdier Snodgrass to his wife Sarah Ann Snodgrass, in Hedgesville, Va., while he was attending a session of the state legislature in Richmond as a delegate. He describes the city of Richmond and a party given by Governor David Campbell, and mentions political colleagues, a military parade, and the failure of the legislature to elect a United States Senator.
Description from the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Manuscript Card Catalog.
Enslaved persons -- West Virginia; Slavery -- West Virginia; Nursing schools -- North Carolina; Berkeley County (W. Va.) -- History -- Anecdotes, facetiae, satire, etc.; West Virginia -- Berkeley County -- Martinsburg; West Virginia -- History -- Sources; Albumen prints; Cellulose nitrate film; Gelatin silver prints; Glass plate negatives; Snodgrass family; Gardiner, Mabel Henshaw; Henshaw family; Gardiner family; Duke University. School of Nursing -- Curricula; Gardiner, Ann Henshaw
- Correspondence, 1779-1980
  - Correspondence, 1779-1859, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1860-1980 and undated, 9 folders (Box 2)
- Diaries, 1825-1967
  - Levi Henshaw (diary and transcript) Nov. 10, 1828-March 25, 1829 (Box 3)
  - Hiram Henshaw (transcript) Jan. 4 1830-May 15 1830 (Box 3)
  - Susan Riddle (transcript) 1861-1864 (Box 3)
  - Ann H. Gardiner 1904-1905 (Box 3)
  - Ann H. Gardiner 1910 (Box 3)
  - Ann H. Gardiner 1911 (Box 3)
  - Ann H. Gardiner 1912 (Box 3)
  - Ann H. Gardiner 1917, vols. 1 & 2 (Box 3)
  - Fanny Henshaw Travel Diary (Western U.S.) 1928 (Box 3)
  - Ann H. Gardiner and Fanny Henshaw (travel diary western U.S.) June-Sept. 1928 (Box 4)
  - Ann H. Gardiner and Fanny Henshaw (travel diary and misc. notes, U.S.) 1929 and 1930s. (Box 4)
  - Mabel H. Gardiner (travel diary southern U.S. - W. Va. to Fla.) 1938 Ann H. Gardiner (travel diary Fla.) 1938 (Box 4)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Exploring the Rocky Mountains (travel diary/scrapbook) 1939 (Box 4)
  - Jo [?] and Ann H. Gardiner (travel diary transcontinental U.S.) 1957 (Box 4)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Greece (travel diary/scrapbook) 1958 (Box 4)
  - Ann H. Gardiner South America (travel diary/scrapbook) 1961 (Box 5)
  - Ann H. Gardiner North With the Birds: Scotland, Norway, Lapland, Finland, Sweden, Denmark (travel diary/scrapbook) June 1962 (Box 5)
  - Ann H. Gardiner By Jet to the South Seas and the South Pacific v. 1 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1963 (Box 6)
  - Ann H. Gardiner By Jet to the South Seas and the South Pacific v. 2 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1963 (Box 6)
  - Ann H. Gardiner By Jet to the South Seas and the South Pacific v. 3 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1963 (Box 7)
  - Ann H. Gardiner The Land of the Pharaohs - Lebanon v. 1 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1964 (Box 7)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Syria, Jordan, Israel, Athens v. 2 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1964 (Box 8)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Greek Isles, Turkey, Greece: The Land of the Gods v. 3 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1964 (Box 8)
  - Ann H. Gardiner The Toltecs, Aztecs, and and the Spaniards v. 1 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1965 (Box 9)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Mayaland v. 2 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1960s 10 DIARIES (Box 9)
  - Ann H. Gardiner The Book of Kells: A Modern Version (travel diary/scrapbook) 1966 (Box 10)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Ireland, England v. 1 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1967 (Box 10)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Holland, Belgium, Luxembourg, Germany, Austria, Yugoslavia v. 2 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1967 (Box 11)
  - Ann H. Gardiner Italy v. 3 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1967 (Box 11)
  - Ann H. Gardiner France, Switzerland, Ireland v. 4 (travel diary/scrapbook) 1967 (Box 11)
- Legal Papers, 1723-1981; 1723-1910
  - Articles of Agreement 1788-1889, undated (Box 12)
  - Bonds 1772-1869 (Box 12)
  - Bounty Land Claims 1845-1855 (Box 12)
  - Deeds 1754-1896, undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Depositions 1825-1858, undated (Box 12)
  - Estate Settlement (Joseph Evans) 1798, undated (Box 12)
  - Estate Settlement (Abraham & William Gorrell) 1826-1856, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Estate Settlement (William B. Gorrell Account Books) ca. 1839-1844 (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (John Gray) 1817-1825 (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (Joseph Grubb) 1833-1835 (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (Levi Henshaw) 1845-1869 (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (Elon Miller & Israel Robinson) 1842-1849, undated (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (Robert Snodgrass) 1823-1861, undated (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (Thomas Turner) 1723-1821, undated, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlement (John White) 1822-1829 (Box 13)
  - Estate Settlements-Miscellaneous 1809-1852 (Box 13)
  - Judgements 1822-1868 (Box 13)
  - Land Office (Berkeley Co., Va.) 1803-1819, undated (Box 13)
  - Land Surveys (Frederick Co., Va.) 1753-1772 (Box 14)
  - Land Surveys (Berkeley Co., Va.) 1774-1888, undated, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Land Surveys (Sleepy Creek) 1751-1805, undated (Box 14)
  - Land Records - Miscellaneous 1775-1856, undated (Box 14)
  - Leases 1783-1909 (Box 14)
  - Liquor Distillery 1809-1816 (Box 14)
  - Military Records 1798-1859, undated (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous 1790-1904, undated (Box 15)
  - Postmaster General (Robert Snodgrass) 1853 (Box 15)
  - Powers of Attorney 1801-l859 (Box 15)
  - Road Orders 1818, undated (Box 15)
  - Sale Bills 1800-1908, undated (Box 15)
  - Summons 1815-1869 (Box 15)
  - Tax Records 1802-1817 (Box 15)
  - Warrants 1809-1868 (Box 15)
  - Wills 1771-1835, 1981 (Box 15)
- Financial Papers, 1798-1921
  - Account Book (Henshaw) 1828-1833 (Box 16)
  - Account Books (Zephaniah & Martha Silver) 1834-1858 (Box 16)
  - Account Books (Snodgrass) 1816-1844 (Box 16)
  - Account Book (Stephen Snodgrass) 1803-1806 (includes birth & death entries of children) (Box 16)
  - Account Book (Jacob Thomas) 1897-1870 (Box 16)
  - Bill & Receipts (G. W. Henshaw & Bros.) Aug 1848- March 1850, undated (Box 16)
  - Bills & Receipts (Levi Henshaw) 1798-1849, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - Bills & Receipts (Levi Henshaw) 1850-1896, undated, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Bills & Receipts (Robert Snodgrass) 1798-1886, undated, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous 1863, 1921, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Back Creek Meeting House) 1817, 1830 (Box 17)
- Genealogical Materials, 19th century-20th century
  - Duvall-Rawlings Family Scrapbook (Box 18)
  - Duvall-Rawlings Family Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Evans Family Scrapbook (Box 18)
  - Henshaw Family Charts (Box 18)
  - Henshaw Family Histories (Box 18)
  - Henshaw Family Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - William Henshaw Chapter of DAR Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Kendall-Cunningham-Snodgrass Family Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Patterson-Snodgrass Family Scrapbook, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Robinson-Snodgrass Family Scrapbook, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Snodgrass Family Age Book and Notebook (Box 20)
  - Snodgrass Family Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Verdier Family Scrapbook (Box 20)
  - Verdier Family Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Unfinished and General (Box 20)
- Photographic Materials, 1860s-1960s
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Some materials in this series are fragile audiovisual/photographic formats in the form of nitrate negatives that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - Family and Friends prints (1 of 2), 1860s-1905 (Box 22)
    - Uncle Steve, circa 1860s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0001)
    - Uncle Thorton Henshaw, 1862 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0002)
    - Sarah Ann Snodgrass, 1866 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0003)
    - Edna Butler, Katie Butler, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0004)
      Scope and Contents
      "Aunt Lilly's children". Tintype
    - Ann Henshaw Gardiner, 1891 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0005)
      "8 months old". Tintype
    - Aunt Lil (Butler), Mary Dorsey, Fanny Henshaw, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0006)
      Tintype
    - Mabel Henshaw, Francis Henshaw, unidentified woman (possibly Virginia Valley Henshaw), circa 1860s-1890s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0007)
    - Mabel Henshaw, Francis Henshaw, unidentified woman (possibly Virginia Valley Henshaw), circa 1860s-1890s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0008)
    - Captain William Henshaw, circa 1808-1815 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0009)
      Mounted copy photo print of painting or drawing.
    - Captain William Henshaw, circa 1808-1815 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0010)
      Copy photo print of painting or drawing.
    - Mrs. I. H. Gardiner, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0011)
      Image is of a child.
    - Unidentified girl, handcolored cabinet card, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0012)
  - Family and Friends prints (2 of 2) (Box 22)
    - Levi Henshaw, Jr., 1890 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0013)
    - Levi Henshaw, Jr., 1890 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0014)
    - Edward Claggett Williams, circa 1910 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0015)
    - Anna Henshaw Gardiner, Robert Gardiner, Charley Emmerson, circa 1900 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0016)
    - Ann Henshaw Gardiner, 1891 February 03 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0017)
    - Ann Henshaw Gardiner, 1891 February 03 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0018)
    - Sarah Ann Snodgrass, circa 1890s-1900s (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0019)
    - Ann Henshaw Gardiner, Robert Gardiner, circa 1897 (Box 22, Image RL00432-I-0020)